<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY standard "Editor's Draft">
<!ENTITY tracker "http://sourceforge.net/tracker">
<!ENTITY RFE "&tracker;/index.php?func=detail&amp;group_id=21935&amp;atid=384107&amp;">
<!ENTITY root "http://docs.oasis-open.org/docbook/">
]>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 version="5.1"
	 xml:lang="en"
	 status="&standard;">
<info>
<releaseinfo role="cvs">
$Id$
</releaseinfo>

<!-- product -->        <productname>docbook</productname>
<!-- productVersion --> <productnumber>5.1b2</productnumber>
<!-- artifactType       spec; what else? :-) -->
<!-- stage -->          <releaseinfo role="stage">ed</releaseinfo>
<!-- revision -->       <biblioid class="pubsnumber">01</biblioid>
<!-- language           en; see /article/@xml:lang -->
<!-- form               xml -->

<releaseinfo role="location">&root;specs</releaseinfo>

<title>The DocBook Schema</title>

<org>
  <orgname>OASIS</orgname>
  <orgdiv xlink:href="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/workgroup.php?wg_abbrev=docbook">OASIS DocBook Technical Committee</orgdiv>
</org>

<othercredit class="other" otherclass="chair">
  <personname>
    <firstname>Norman</firstname>
    <surname>Walsh</surname>
  </personname>
  <email>norman.walsh@marklogic.com</email>
  <affiliation>
    <orgname>MarkLogic Corporation</orgname>
  </affiliation>
</othercredit>

<authorgroup>
<editor>
  <personname>
    <firstname>Norman</firstname>
    <surname>Walsh</surname>
  </personname>
  <email>norman.walsh@marklogic.com</email>
  <affiliation>
    <orgname>MarkLogic Corporation</orgname>
  </affiliation>
</editor>
</authorgroup>

<pubdate>2010-07-27</pubdate>

<bibliomisc role="namespace">http://docbook.org/ns/docbook</bibliomisc>

<!--
<bibliorelation type="replaces" condition="online"
    xlink:href="http://docbook.org/specs/docbook-5.0-spec-cd-05.html"/>
-->

<bibliorelation type="references" condition="online"
    xlink:href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/docbook/specs/docbook-5.0-spec-os.html"/>

<!--
<bibliorelation type="references" condition="print"
    xlink:href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/docbook/specs/docbook-5.0-spec-os.pdf"/>
-->

<copyright>
<year>2001</year><year>2002</year><year>2003</year>
<year>2004</year><year>2005</year><year>2006</year>
<year>2007</year><year>2008</year><year>2009</year>
<year>2010</year>
<holder>The Organization for the Advancement of Structured Information
Standards [OASIS]. All Rights Reserved. </holder></copyright>

<abstract>
<para>DocBook is a general purpose <xref linkend="xml-rec"/> schema
particularly well suited to books and papers about computer hardware
and software (though it is by no means limited to these applications).
</para>
<para>The Technical Committee provides the DocBook 5.1 schema in other
schema languages, including W3C XML Schema and an
XML DTD, but the RELAX NG Schema is now the normative schema.</para>
</abstract>

<legalnotice role="status">
<!--
<para>This &standard; was
<link xlink:href="...">approved</link>
for publication by the
OASIS DocBook Technical Committee. It represents the
consensus of the committee.
</para>
-->

<para>This is a &standard;. It does not necessarily
represent the consensus of the committee.
</para>

<para>Please send comments on this specification to the
<email>docbook@lists.oasis-open.org</email> list. To subscribe, please
use the
<link xlink:href="http://lists.oasis-open.org/ob/adm.pl">OASIS Subscription
Manager</link>.</para>

<!--
<para>The errata page for this specification is at
<link xlink:href="&root;specs/docbook5-errata.html"/>.
</para>
-->
</legalnotice>

<legalnotice role="notices">
<para>Copyright © OASIS® 2010. All Rights Reserved.</para>

<para>All capitalized terms in the following text have the meanings
assigned to them in the OASIS Intellectual Property Rights Policy (the
"OASIS IPR Policy"). The full Policy may be found at the OASIS
website.</para>

<para>This document and translations of it may be copied and furnished
to others, and derivative works that comment on or otherwise explain
it or assist in its implementation may be prepared, copied, published,
and distributed, in whole or in part, without restriction of any kind,
provided that the above copyright notice and this section are included
on all such copies and derivative works. However, this document itself
may not be modified in any way, including by removing the copyright
notice or references to OASIS, except as needed for the purpose of
developing any document or deliverable produced by an OASIS Technical
Committee (in which case the rules applicable to copyrights, as set
forth in the OASIS IPR Policy, must be followed) or as required to
translate it into languages other than English.</para>

<para>The limited permissions granted above are perpetual and will not
be revoked by OASIS or its successors or assigns.</para>

<para>This document and the information contained herein is provided
on an "AS IS" basis and OASIS DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR
IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE
INFORMATION HEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY OWNERSHIP RIGHTS OR ANY
IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
PURPOSE.</para>

<para>OASIS requests that any OASIS Party or any other party that
believes it has patent claims that would necessarily be infringed by
implementations of this OASIS Committee Specification or OASIS
Standard, to notify OASIS TC Administrator and provide an indication
of its willingness to grant patent licenses to such patent claims in a
manner consistent with the IPR Mode of the OASIS Technical Committee
that produced this specification.</para>

<para>OASIS invites any party to contact the OASIS TC Administrator if
it is aware of a claim of ownership of any patent claims that would
necessarily be infringed by implementations of this specification by a
patent holder that is not willing to provide a license to such patent
claims in a manner consistent with the IPR Mode of the OASIS Technical
Committee that produced this specification. OASIS may include such
claims on its website, but disclaims any obligation to do so.</para>

<para>OASIS takes no position regarding the validity or scope of any
intellectual property or other rights that might be claimed to pertain
to the implementation or use of the technology described in this
document or the extent to which any license under such rights might or
might not be available; neither does it represent that it has made any
effort to identify any such rights. Information on OASIS' procedures
with respect to rights in any document or deliverable produced by an
OASIS Technical Committee can be found on the OASIS website. Copies of
claims of rights made available for publication and any assurances of
licenses to be made available, or the result of an attempt made to
obtain a general license or permission for the use of such proprietary
rights by implementers or users of this OASIS Committee Specification
or OASIS Standard, can be obtained from the OASIS TC Administrator.
OASIS makes no representation that any information or list of
intellectual property rights will at any time be complete, or that any
claims in such list are, in fact, Essential Claims.</para>

<para>The name "OASIS" is a trademark of OASIS, the owner and
developer of this specification, and should be used only to refer to
the organization and its official outputs. OASIS welcomes reference
to, and implementation and use of, specifications, while reserving the
right to enforce its marks against misleading uses. Please see
<link xlink:href="http://www.oasis-open.org/who/trademark.php"/>
for above guidance.</para>
</legalnotice>
</info>

<section xml:id="s.intro">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>DocBook is general purpose XML schema
particularly well suited to books and papers about computer hardware
and software (though it is by no means limited to these applications).
</para>

<para>The <link xlink:href="mailto:docbook-tc@oasis-open.org">DocBook
Technical Committee</link> maintains the DocBook schema. Starting
with V5.0, DocBook is normatively available as a <xref
linkend="iso19757-2"/> Schema (with some additional
<xref linkend="iso19757-3"/> assertions).
W3C XML Schema and Document Type
Definition (DTD) versions are also available.
</para>

<para>The Version 5.1 release adds a major new feature to DocBook: the
ability to compose document assemblies specifically designed to be
suitable for use in topic-based authoring methodologies.
It also adds a <tag>topic</tag> element, in support of
topic-based authoring, and fixes a small number of bugs.</para>

<para>The DocBook Technical Committee welcomes bug reports and
requests for enhancement (RFEs) from the user community. The current list
of outstanding requests is available through the
<link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/">SourceForge</link>
<link xlink:href="&tracker;/?atid=384107&amp;group_id=21935&amp;func=browse">tracker</link>
interface. This is also the preferred mechanism for submitting new requests.
</para>

<section xml:id="s.terminology">
<title>Terminology</title>

<section xml:id="s.keywords">
<title>Key words</title>

<para>The key words <glossterm>must</glossterm>, <glossterm>must
not</glossterm>, <glossterm>required</glossterm>,
<glossterm>shall</glossterm>, <glossterm>shall not</glossterm>,
<glossterm>should</glossterm>, <glossterm>should not</glossterm>,
<glossterm>recommended</glossterm>, <glossterm>may</glossterm>, and
<glossterm>optional</glossterm> in this &standard; are to be
interpreted as described in <xref linkend="rfc2119"/>. Note that for
reasons of style, these words are not capitalized in this
document.</para>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="normative.refs">
<title>Normative References</title>

<bibliolist>
<bibliomixed xml:id="xml-rec"/>
<bibliomixed xml:id="xlink11"/>
<bibliomixed xml:id="xmlschema-2"/>
<bibliomixed xml:id="iso19757-2"/>
<bibliomixed xml:id="iso19757-3"/>
<bibliomixed xml:id="rfc2119"/>
<bibliomixed xml:id="rfc3023"/>
<bibliomixed xml:id="bib.docbooktdg5"/>
</bibliolist>
</section>

<section xml:id="non-normative.refs">
<title>Non-Normative References</title>

<bibliolist>
<bibliomixed xml:id="iso8879"/>
<bibliomixed xml:id="xmlschema-1"/>
</bibliolist>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="s.docbook">
<title>The DocBook RELAX NG Schema</title>

<para>This release is DocBook V5.1b2.</para>

<para>Summary of changes in 5.1 TBD.</para>

<para>Changes since 5.1b1:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Created a <code>db.any.docbook</code> pattern that matches any single DocBook pattern. This pattern
allows, for example, the <tag>resource</tag> element to contain text or any (single) valid DocBook element.
(Allowing for more than one element would introduce the possibility of invalid combinations that would not
be easy to detect.)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added <tag class="attribute">renderas</tag> to <tag>structure</tag>. Changed <tag class="attribute">renderas</tag>
(in at least these contexts) to be a <type>QName</type>).
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added <tag>override</tag> to <tag>structure</tag>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Took <tag>info</tag> out of <tag>relationship</tag> and put <tag>association</tag> back in.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Fixed content model of <tag>book</tag> and <tag>part</tag> to make <tag>topic</tag> an alternative and not
part of the component mixture.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Fixed a few pattern typos in <filename>assembly-core.rnc</filename>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Make <tag>structure</tag> optional in <tag>assembly</tag>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Removed the <tag class="attribute">description</tag> attribute from assemblies. No human readable content in
attribute values! (This has turned out to be someone contentious within the Technical Committee.)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Added more documentation, though it's still far from complete.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Requests for enhancement addressed in 5.1b1:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>RFE <link xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;group_id=21935&amp;atid=384107&amp;aid=1679665">1679665</link>
Add better support for modular documentation
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>RFE <link xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;group_id=21935&amp;atid=384107&amp;aid=1722935">1722935</link>
Add a <tag class="attvalue">proofreader</tag> value to the <tag class="attribute">class</tag>
attribute for <tag>othercredit</tag>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>RFE <link xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;group_id=21935&amp;atid=384107&amp;aid=1770787">1770787</link>
Add <tag>givenname</tag> as an alternative for <tag>firstname</tag>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>RFE <link xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;group_id=21935&amp;atid=384107&amp;aid=1899655">1899655</link>
Allow more elements to be the root of a DocBook document
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>RFE <link xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;group_id=21935&amp;atid=384107&amp;aid=2100736">2100736</link>
Allow <tag>constant</tag> in <tag>initializer</tag>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>RFE <link xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;group_id=21935&amp;atid=384107&amp;aid=2791288">2791288</link>
Added several additional elements, including <tag>quote</tag>, to the ubiquitous inlines
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>RFE <link xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;group_id=21935&amp;atid=384107&amp;aid=2820190">2820190</link>
Add a <tag>topic</tag> element
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>RFE <link xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;group_id=21935&amp;atid=384107&amp;aid=2821653">2821653</link>
Remove the constraint that <tag>indexterm</tag> elements must not appear in
<tag>footnote</tag>s
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>RFE <link xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;group_id=21935&amp;atid=384107&amp;aid=2907124">2907124</link>
Allow personal name components directly in <tag>bibliomset</tag>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>RFE <link xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;group_id=21935&amp;atid=384107&amp;aid=2907125">2907125</link>
Allow all inlines in <tag>remark</tag>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>RFE <link xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;group_id=21935&amp;atid=384107&amp;aid=2907131">2907131</link>
Allow <tag>simplesect</tag> in <tag>colophon</tag>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>RFE <link xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;group_id=21935&amp;atid=384107&amp;aid=2964576">2964576</link>
Fix the bug that allowed <tag>table</tag> to appear inside <tag>entry</tag>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</section>

<section xml:id="s.identifying">
<title>Identifying DocBook Documents and Schemas</title>

<para>Historically, when DocBook was defined by a DTD, DocBook
documents could be identified by the presence of standard public
and/or system identifiers in the document type declaration. RELAX NG,
the normative schema language for DocBook V5.1, does not provide
any equivalent mechanism.</para>

<para>For systems that can make use of public identifiers, e.g., systems
where the informative DTD is being used, the following
public identifier can be used for DocBook V5.1:
“<literal>-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V5.1//EN//XML</literal>”.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="s.conformance">
<title>Conformance</title>

<para>This specification normatively defines DocBook V5.1 with a RELAX NG
grammar and a set of Schematron assertions. A conformant DocBook V5.1 document
<glossterm>must</glossterm> be valid according to both the grammar and the
assertions.</para>

<para>The reference documentation describes additional constraints and
processing expectations. A conformant DocBook V5.1 document
<glossterm>should</glossterm> respect those constraints and anticipate
those processing expectations.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="backwards-compatibility">
<title>Backwards compatibility</title>

<para>The DocBook Technical Committee understands that the community
benefits from the long-term stability of the DocBook family of
schemas. We also understand that DocBook must continue to adapt and
change in order to remain relevant in a changing world.</para>

<para>All changes, and especially changes that are backwards
incompatible (changes that make a currently valid document no longer
valid under a new version of the schema), have a cost associated with
them. Our duty is to balance those costs against the need to remain
responsive to the community's desire to see DocBook grow to cover the
new use cases that inevitably arise in documentation.</para>

<para>With that in mind, the DocBook Technical Committee has adopted
the following policy on backwards incompatible changes. This policy
spells out when backwards incompatible changes can occur and how much
notice the TC must provide before adopting a schema that is backwards
incompatible with the current release.</para>

<para>This policy allows DocBook to continue to change and adapt while
simultaneously guaranteeing that existing users will have sufficient
advance notice to develop reasonable migration plans.</para>

<para>With respect to schema changes, the following points
<glossterm>must</glossterm> always apply:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>A point release (X.1 to X.2, X.2 to X.3, X.1 to X.1.2, etc.)
<glossterm>must not</glossterm> contain any backwards incompatible changes
unless those changes correct obvious bugs accidentally
introduced in the preceding
version.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A major release (X.1 to Y.0, X.2 to Y.0, X.1.2 to Y.0, etc.)
<glossterm>may</glossterm> contain backwards incompatible changes if
both of the following conditions are true:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The change was announced in the release notes for the previous
version (major or minor).</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The change was announced in a release that occurred at least six
months previously.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>By these rules, the TC can announce, in V5.1 for example, its
plans to make a backwards incompatible change in V6.0. Then, in V6.0,
if it's been at least six months since V5.1 was released, it can make
that change.</para>

<para>The exclusion in point 1 is
designed to allow the committee to correct errors accidentally
introduced in a point release, that are technically backwards
incompatible, without having to leave them in the schema until the next
full version.
</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="s.relnotes">
<title>Release Notes</title>

<para>See <link xlink:href="http://www.relaxng.org/"/> for a list of tools that
can validate an XML document using RELAX NG. Note that not all products
are capable of evaluating the Schematron assertions in the schema.</para>

<section xml:id="s.bic-60">
<title>Backwards Incompatible Changes Planned for DocBook V6.0</title>

<para>The following backwards incompatible changes are planned for
DocBook V6.0:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The linking elements will be removed from the content model of
<tag>biblioid</tag>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The common linking attributes will be removed from <tag>indexterm</tag>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">xml:id</tag> attribute will be made
required on <tag class="attribute">startofrange</tag> <tag>indexterms</tag>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A Schematron constraint will be added to assert that for every
<tag class="attribute">startofrange</tag>
<tag>indexterm</tag> there is exactly one
<tag class="attribute">endofrange</tag> <tag>indexterm</tag>
that points to it.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">language</tag> attribute will be removed from
<tag>address</tag>; use <tag class="attribute">xml:lang</tag> instead.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
</section>

<appendix xml:id="a.mimetype">
<title>The DocBook Media Type</title>

<para>This appendix registers a new MIME media type,
<quote><code>application/docbook+xml</code></quote>.</para>

<section xml:id="media-type-registration">
<title>Registration of MIME media type application/docbook+xml</title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>MIME media type name:</term>
<listitem>
<para><code>application</code>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>MIME subtype name:</term>
<listitem>
<para><code>docbook+xml</code>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Required parameters:</term>
<listitem>
<para>None.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Optional parameters:</term>
<listitem>
  <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><code>charset</code></term>
  <listitem>

  <para>This parameter has identical semantics to the <code>charset</code>
parameter of the <code>application/xml</code> media type as
specified in <xref linkend="rfc3023"/> or its successors.
</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Encoding considerations:</term>
<listitem>
<para>By virtue of DocBook XML content being XML, it has the same
considerations when sent as <quote><code>application/docbook+xml</code></quote>
as does XML. See <xref linkend="rfc3023"/>, Section 3.2.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Security considerations:</term>
<listitem>
<para>Several DocBook elements may refer to arbitrary URIs.
In this case, the security issues of RFC 2396, section 7,
should be considered.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Interoperability considerations:</term>
<listitem>
<para>None.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Published specification:</term>
<listitem>
<para>This media type registration is for DocBook documents as described by
<xref linkend="bib.docbooktdg5"/>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Applications which use this media type:</term>
<listitem>
<para>There is no experimental, vendor specific, or personal tree
predecessor to <quote><code>application/docbook+xml</code></quote>,
reflecting the fact that no applications currently recognize it. This
new type is being registered in order to allow for the
deployment of DocBook on the World Wide Web, as a first class XML
application.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Additional information:</term>
<listitem>
  <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
  <term>Magic number(s):</term>

  <listitem>
  <para>There is no single initial octet sequence that is always present in
DocBook documents.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
  <term>File extension(s):</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>DocBook documents are most often identified with the extension
<quote><filename class="extension">.xml</filename></quote>.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
  <term>Macintosh File Type Code(s):</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>TEXT</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:</term>
<listitem>
<para>Norman Walsh, <email>ndw@nwalsh.com</email>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Intended usage:</term>
<listitem>
<para>COMMON</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Author/Change controller:</term>
<listitem>
<para>The DocBook specification is a work product of the DocBook
Technical Committee at OASIS.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>

<section xml:id="fragid">
<title>Fragment Identifiers</title>

<para>For documents labeled as
<quote><code>application/docbook+xml</code></quote>,
the fragment
identifier notation is exactly that for
<quote><code>application/xml</code></quote>,
as specified in <xref linkend="rfc3023"/> or its successors.</para>
</section>
</appendix>

<appendix xml:id="a.committee" role="non-normative">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>

<para>The following individuals have participated in the creation of
this specification and are gratefully acknowledged:</para>

<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
<title>Participants</title>
<listitem><para>Gary Cornelius, Individual</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Paul Grosso, Arbortext</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Dick Hamilton, Individual</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Nancy Harrison, IBM</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Scott Hudson, Individual</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Gershon Joseph, Tech-Tav Documentation Ltd.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Jirka Kosek, Individual</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Larry Rowland, Hewlett-Packard</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Robert Stayton, Individual (Secretary)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Norman Walsh, MarkLogic Corporation (Chair, Editor)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</appendix>

<appendix xml:id="changes">
<title>Revision History</title>

<!--
<listitem xml:id="rfe.">
<para>Fixed <link xlink:href="&RFE;aid=">RFE </link>:

</para>
</listitem>
-->

<para>This specification does not yet reflect any schema changes.</para>

</appendix>

</article>
